A Guide to the John Janney Papers, 1811-1994 (Bulk 1840-1880)
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
John Janney Papers, 1811-1994 (Bulk, 1840-188)
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2001-019
8.0 cu. ft. 19 boxes
The John Janney Papers consist of over 800 letters written to John Janney and members of his family. Other materials include biographical information, books, and periodicals.
Janney, John, 1798-1872
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The John Janney Papers were donated to Special Collections in 2000.
Biographical Information
On November 8, 1798, John Janney was born in Alexandria, Virginia, to Elisha and Mary Janney. The Janneys were members of the religious denomination of Friends or Quakers. Janney obtained little formal education, instead going to work at his father's mill. He later left the mill to study law, and at the age of eighteen, he entered the Bar in Loudoun County. On January 26, 1826, Janney married Alcinda (Alice) Marmaduke. When separated, they wrote almost daily letters to one another.
Janney became a respected lawyer and in 1850 he represented Loudoun County at the Virginia Constitutional Convention. Janney also served his state when he accepted the position as President of the Virginia Secession Convention in 1861. As a strong Whig and Unionist, Janney fought against secession and voted against it twice. When secession finally passed, Janney embraced it fully. He signed the Ordinance of Secession and formally appointed Robert E. Lee as commander of military forces of Virginia. Janney continued to serve as a lawyer in Loudoun until his death in 1872.
Charles Janney, nephew of John Janney, was born May 27, 1839 to James and Rebecca Janney. Charles Janney attended the Benjamin Hallowell School in Alexandria, Virginia until his eighteenth birthday. After graduation, Janney worked at his father's flour mill while also studying the law. Janney ran for office and was elected clerk of the county court for Loudoun and served in that position until he entered the Bar in 1871. In 1921, he was elected as mayor of Leesburg and served for two years.
Charles Janney married Nannie Lee Pollock on November 23, 1868. They had eight children: Thomas, Rebecca, Lilas, Charles P., A.D. Pollock, Phillip, Nannie, and John.
Scope and Content
The John Janney Papers consist of over 800 letters written to John Janney and members of his family. The most influential letters are ones written between John Janney and his wife while Janney served as President of the Virginia Secession Convention. In these letters Janney gives brief details of the Convention and comments on the other delegates in attendance. Other letters are between Charles Janney and his wife and family. The bulk of the letters describe legal matters and are from John Janney's years as a practicing lawyer. Additional materials include biographical information, books, and periodicals.
Images from this collection are available on Imagebase.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into three series:
Series I: Biographical Information is arranged in four subseries: John Janney, Charles Janney, Journal of the Convention, and Miscellaneous Government Documents. This series includes biographical information, newspapers, inventory of property, and Convention minutes. Each subseries is arranged chronologically.
Series II: Correspondence is arranged in ten subseries: John Janney with Alice Janney (wife); Alice Janney with John Janney; Janney Family Letters; Letters to Alice Janney; Pollock Family Papers; Charles Janney Papers; John Janney Letters; John Janney Legal Letters and Court Cases; Court Cases; and Miscallenous Letters.
Series III: Books, Periodicals, and Media is arranged in three subseries: Books, Periodicals, and Media.
Index Terms
Persons:
Janney, John, 1798-1872
Family Names:
Janney family
Local Subjects:
Civil War; Local/Regional History
Contents List
- Biographical, 1850-1994, n.d.
  - John Janney, 1861-1994, n.d.
    - Speech given by Wilbur C. Hall, Chairman of the VA Conservation Commission to the Rotary Club. Contains 27 page biography including acceptance speech to Robert E. Lee. (Box-folder 1:1)
    - Loudoun County and the Civil War. 3 page entry on the life of John Janney. (Box-folder 1:2)
    - Virginia Magazine of History and Biography, Vol. 102, No. 3. Short, incomplete biography, July 1994. (Box-folder 1:3)
    - Passages from Virginia's Attitude Toward Slavery and Secession, by Beverley Mumford, Oct 1909. Janney's acceptance speech to the Secession Convention, 1909. (Box-folder 1:4)
    - Speech by Janney to the Secession Convention. (Box-folder 1:5)
    - Janney's discussion with Robert E. Lee before and after Gettysburg. (Box-folder 1:6)
    - Biographical Register of Members, Virginia State Convention of 1861. 1 page biography of Janney, by the VA State Library, 1969. (Box-folder 1:7)
    - Speech from Janney to Lee, charging Lee with command of military forces in Virginia and Lee's response, April 23, 1861. (Box-folder 1:8)
    - Janney's speech to the Convention accepting the Presidency. (Box-folder 1:9)
    - Congressional Record of the House. Janney missed being President of the United States by one vote. (Box-folder 1:10)
    - Congressional Record of the House. Janney elected President of the Convention, his acceptance speech, and Charge to Lee to command Virginia's forces. (Box-folder 1:11)
    - Journal of the Acts and Proceedings of a General Convention of the State of Virginia. (Box-folder 1:12)
    - Unfinished history of Janney written by Major John M. Orr, 1890s. (Box-folder 1:13)
    - Story of Janney Collection. Janney's nephew married into the Lee Family, Loudoun Times Mirror, August 3, 1967. (Box-folder 1:14)
    - Food account, 1862. (Box-folder 1:15)
    - Janney's payments, 1811-1817. (Box-folder 1:16)
    - Inventory for the sale of Alice Janney's possessions, October 8, 1878. (Box-folder 12:2)
    - John Janney - Last Will and Testament, March 1, 1866 (Box-folder 1:17a)
  - Charles Janney, 1922.
    - Janney Family - History and genealogical information, 1922; 1932. (Box-folder 1:17)
  - Journal of the Convention, 1861.
    - Journal of the Convention, November 13, 1861. (Box-folder 1:18)
    - Journal of the Convention, November 16, 1861. (Box-folder 1:19)
    - Journal of the Convention, November 18, 1861. (Box-folder 1:20)
    - Journal of the Convention, November 19, 1861. (Box-folder 1:21)
    - Journal of the Convention, November 20, 1861. (Box-folder 1:22)
    - Journal of the Convention, November 21, 1861. (Box-folder 1:23)
    - Journal of the Convention, November 22, 1861. (Box-folder 1:24)
    - Journal of the Convention, November 25, 1861. (Box-folder 1:25)
    - Journal of the Convention, November 26, 1861. (Box-folder 1:26)
    - Journal of the Convention, November 27, 1861. (Box-folder 1:27)
    - Journal of the Convention, November 28, 1861. (Box-folder 1:28)
    - Journal of the Convention, November 29, 1861. (Box-folder 1:29)
    - Journal of the Convention, November 30, 1861. (Box-folder 1:30)
  - Government documents, 1850-1866.
    - Plan proposed to the committee on the judiciary by John Janney, 1850. (Box-folder 12:4)
    - Pages from the Reconstruction Interviews, 1866. (Box-folder 1:31)
- Correspondence, 1836-1907.
  - John Janney with Alice Janney, 1861-1868. (Box-folder 2:1-2:27, 3:1-3:44 (71 folders))
  - Alice Janney with John Janney, 1861, 1867. (Box-folder 4:1-4:17 (17 folders))
  - Janney Family Letters, 1868-1890.
    - Political letter to John Janney from N. Janney from St. Louis—discusses politicts over state banks, hard currency, and Van Buren, 1836. (Box-folder 12:4)
    - Letters from Nathaniel Janney to Charles and Nannie Janney, 1868. (Box-folder 4:18)
    - Letters from Nathaniel Janney to Charles and Nannie Janney, 1871. (Box-folder 4:19)
    - Letters from John B. Janney to Rebecca Janney, 1871. (Box-folder 4:20)
    - John B. Janney to his Mother—dealt with the raising of Lee Statue, 1890. (Box-folder 4:21)
    - Letters to Phinnas Janney from Henry Miller David. (Box-folder 4:22)
    - Letters from Lizzy (Alice Janney's live in girl). (Box-folder 4:23)
      Scope and Contents note
      January 18, to Alice
      March 21, to Mrs. J
      June 10, to Charlie
      August 21, to her Pa
      August 30, to My darling father
      August 25, to My Darling father
  - Letters to Alice Janney, dealing with the sickness and death of John Janney, 1871-1878, n.d.
    - Letters to Alice Janney, 1871. (Box-folder 4:24)
      February 4, Philadelphia
      February 7, Norfolk, from S.K. Jackson
      March 27, Alexandria, from her sister
      August, from Minra?
      August 21
      August 22, from her sister
      September 11, Peirce Valley, from Lizzy Delaney
      September 29, George Town
      October 17
      November 20, Baltimore, Niece Mary
      November 21, Baltimore, Niece S.H. Miluary?
      December 11, Philadelphia, from Hodge
      December 12, Shepherdstown, from E Frary
      December 25, Baltimore, from Niece Mary
      December 28, Baltimore, from Niece Mary
      unreadable
    - Letters to Alice Janney, 1872. (Box-folder 4:25)
      January 8, Baltimore, from Eliza Hinkle
      January 8, from Maggie
      January 12, Washington, unreadable
      January 14, Brooklyn, from Mark
      January 15, Ashton, from Mary
      January 24, Louisville, unreadable
      January 26, Baltimore, from Laura Maddy
      January 26, Georgetown, unknown
      January 28, Philadelphia, from John Hail
      January 29, Warm Springs, unreadable
      February 3, Ridgeway, from Dorcas
      February 21, Mr. Vernon St., from E Waterman
      March 16, Saint Louis, from Charles Miller
    - Letters to Alice Janney, 1872. (Box-folder 4:26)
      January 14, from a niece
      January 15, Baltimore, from Mary
      January 21, Philadelphia, From a cousin
      January 21, Baltimore, from Mary
      January 22, Philadelphia, from Riffliomakers?
      February 12, Lake Home, from a niece
      February 20, Bell Brook, from S. Koler?
      February 21, Kate Marmaduke (Sister)
      March 3, Alexandria, from Ellen Miller
      March 14, Lake Home, from Mary
      March 17, Lexington, from Mary
      From Susan Janney
    - Letters to Alice Janney, 1878. (Box-folder 5:1)
      April 21, Ashton, from Mary
      June 4, Brooklyn, from CA Smart?
      June 30, Ashton, from Mary
      August 28, Sunnyside, from Mary
    - Letters to Alice Janney, 1878. (Box-folder 5:2)
      May 7, Warrenton, from Charles Pollock
      August 7, Leesburg, from Charles Janney (Nephew)
      August 19, Leesburg, from Charles Janney (nephew)
      October 3, Philadelphia, from Janresll Janney (Nephew)
    - Letters to Alice Janney. (Box-folder 5:3)
      June 28, from unreadable
      July 7, Alexandria, from Lucy Pracell
      November, 24, Fort Hamilton, from let Mark
      From Amelid Hart
      From Anna (sister)
      August 28, from Adda
      March, from Nelly
  - Pollock Family Papers, Including Nannie (Pollock) Janney, 1864-1907, n.d.
    - Letters to Nannie (Pollock) Janney, 1864-1865. (Box-folder 5:4)
      February 9, Coles Ferry, from Edwin King—Nannie's brother Thomas was killed during Pickett's Charge
      February 15, unknown sender—ble to get supplies from Yankee's (Greg's Cavalry). Guerrillas busy, and picketts firing every night. Relations between women and Yankee officers. Nannie told to order dresses through Gen. Stuart and Major Mosby.
      February 21, Leeton Forest, from AD Pollock (Nannie's Father)—Christian Commission revivialing religion in Warrington, hoping no more churches will be torn down.
      July 13, Sharon, from Lizzy
      November 15, Cedar Grove, from E. R.
      December 9, from A D Pollock (father)
    - Letters to and from Nannie (Pollock) Janney, 1868. (Box-folder 5:5)
      February 20, Leeton Forest, from Nannie to unknown
      June 23, Richmond, from unknown
    - Pollock Family letters, 1868. (Box-folder 5:6)
      August 12, Leeton Forest, from Margaret to her father AD Pollock
      August 18, Leeton Forest, from Nannie Janney to her father AD Pollock
    - Letter from Mrs. Pollock to Mr. Pollock during the War, c.1861-1865. (Box-folder 5:7)
    - Pollock Papers, 1872-1876. (Box-folder 5:8)
      March 9, 1872 legal paper
      February 4, 1872, debits paper
      May 16, 1876, Wilmington, to Rev Pollock from unreadable
    - Application for the Southern Cross for Thomas Gordon Pollock, 1907. (Box-folder 5:9)
    - Letters to Nannie (Pollock) Janney. (Box-folder 5:10)
      From MLG
      February 22, From P L
      July 6, from AD Pollock (father)
      August 10, from Bell
      October 22, Middleburg, A.D.P. (father)
      November 7, from unknown
      November 12, Leeton Forest, from A. P.
      From A.D.P (father)
    - Letter to AD Pollock from his son. (Box-folder 5:11)
    - Letters between AD Pollock and his Wife. (Box-folder 5:12)
      September 3, From EG Pollock to AD Pollock
      From AD Pollock to his wife
  - Charles Janney Papers, 1864-1891.
    - Letters to Charles Janney, 1864. (Box-folder 5:13)
      February 16, Leeton Forest, from his father
      February 29, Baltimore, from Alice Janney
    - Letters to Charles Janney, 1865. (Box-folder 5:14)
      March 25, Circleville, from Nath Janney (brother)
      July 10, note to Charles
      August 21, Baltimore, from Mortuner Ashburn
    - Letters to Charles and Nannie Janney, 1866. (Box-folder 5:15)
      January 19, Home, from AD Pollock to Nannie (daughter)
      February 25, from a cousin
      March 22, Philadelphia, from Nath Janney (Brother)
      Note
    - Letters to Charles Janney, 1867. (Box-folder 5:16)
      January 12, Philadelphia, from Nath Janney (brother)
      March 30, Philadelphia, Nath Janney
      May 28, Richmond Dispatch Office
      August 15, Bath Alum, From Alice Janney (aunt)
    - Letters to Charles Janney, 1868. (Box-folder 5:17)
      March 12, Hillsboro, from his father
      August 19, Baltimore, from J Z
      August 28, Stearling Spring, from A Janney
      September 3, Leeton Forest, from LSP
      September 19, from unknown
      September 28, from LSP
      October 21, Alexandria, from R. Miller
    - Letters from Charles Janney, 1871. (Box-folder 5:18)
      May 20, Leesburg, to unknown
      December 29, Leesburg, to unknown
    - Letters to Charles Janney from Nathaniel Janney, 1878. (Box-folder 5:19)
      January 18, Philadelphia
      January 20, 1878, from Robert (brother)
      June 2, 1878, Philadelphia, from Robert (brother)
      July 25, Philadelphia
      August 28, Philadelphia
    - Charles Janney Letters, 1891. (Box-folder 5:20)
      May 5, Washington, from M F Morris
      May 15, Washington, from Charles to his Aunt Mildred
      June 3, Washington, from M F Morris
      June 11, Delaware, from Mildred (aunt)
      November 18, Delaware, from Mildred (aunt)
    - Charles Janney Letters, 1865-1890, n.d. (Box-folder 5:21)
      September 25, 1865, Tabbott, from Sue
      August 13, Alexandria, from Alice Janney
      August 29, 1874, Ball Brook, from Alice Janney (aunt)
      March 22, 1885, Philadelphia, from Robert (brother)
      March 19, 1890, Delaware, from Margaut, Covell (cousin)
      November 28, Washington (French Spoliation Claims) from William Earl
      March 8, 1864, Leesburg, to Charles Janney (brother)
      1866, Westtown, to Charles Janney (brother)
  - John Janney Letters, 1828-1871
    - Letter by John Janney to William Brandfield(?), 1840. (Box-folder 6:1)
    - Letter from John to Charles Janney (brothers), 1864. (Box-folder 6:2)
    - Letters from John Janney, 1866-1867. (Box-folder 6:3)
      May 1866, Westtown, Beathers
      May 21, 1866, Washington, to CP Janney (cousin)
      February 22, 1867, Leesburg, to unreadable
      May 8, 1867, Leesburg, to William Rives
      May 10, 1867, Leesburg, to William Rives—Janney trying to start education for women
      June 27, 1867, Leesburg, John Klum
    - Letters from John Janney. (Box-folder 6:4)
      To Anthony Rogers
      Unknown
    - Letters to John Janney, 1828. (Box-folder 12:5)
      February 5, from J. Ashburn
      March 17, from Asa Rogers, Middleburg—Conversation with General Rust about changes against Adams and Clay in the last Presidential election.
    - Letters to John Janney, 1831-1838. (Box-folder 6:5)
      June 13, 1831, from Gen. W F Smith
      December 5. 1832. Alexandria, form JW Heivett
      March 21, 1838, Baltimore, from AG
    - Letter to John Janney from Leigh—dealing with political content, the Virginia Assembly, and Van Buren bribes, December 20, 1835. (Box-folder 12:6)
    - Legal document for the Justice of the Peace of Warren County Mississippi, 1837. (Box-folder 6:7)
    - Letters to John Janney, 1837. (Box-folder 6:8)
      August 17, from John Janney to Philip Heater
      October 21, Baltimore, from Henry Jacobsen
    - Letters to John Janney, 1838. (Box-folder 6:9)
      February 1, Richmond, from Wall hall
      August 15, Auburn, from A Buckern
    - Letters from G. M. Buckley, 1839. (Box-folder 6:10)
      July 3, St. Louis
      July 8, St. Louis
      September 24, St. Louis
      October 14, St. Louis
    - Letters to John Janney, 1839. (Box-folder 6:11)
      July 29, Baltimore, from Williams and Scilly
      From R. Taylor
    - Letters to John Janney, 1840. (Box-folder 6:12)
      July 5, from Sam Upton
      October 28, Baltimore, from unreadable
      December 5, from Mctharney(?)
      December 11, Union, from Garrett
    - John Janney Letters, 1841. (Box-folder 6:13)
      February 25, from Janney to Unknown
      June 4, Leesburg, from John Janney to William Powell
      July 2, Leesburg, from Janney to J Anthony
      December 15, Loudoun, from Upton
    - John Janney Letters, 1841. (Box-folder 6:14)
      February 4
      April 20, Baltimore, from Brooks
      September 10, from John Janney
      October 1, George Town, from Smith
      October 18, Warrenton, from J Scott
      November 1, unreadable
      November 26, Turn Spring, from J Marth?
    - John Janney Letters, 1841. (Box-folder 6:15)
      June 15, Office Dist, Sam Edwards
      Loudoun, from Timothy Taylor
    - Letter to John Janney about buying a slave, 1842. (Box-folder 6:16)
    - John Janney Letters, 1842. (Box-folder 6:17)
      March 1, Middleburg, from Week Gibron?
      March 2, unreadable
      March 4, Philadelphia, from Robin Walkers
      March 4, Baltimore, form Wyeth and Norris
      March 5, Philadelphia, from Roland Nalses?
      March 7, Baltimore, from Geo Baughmany
      March 8, Forest Hill, from George Hamilton
      March 23, Georgetown, unreadable
    - John Janney Letters, 1842. (Box-folder 6:18)
      March 24, from PD shepherd
      April 6, Leesburg, from Bolhinez?
      April 19, Rockland, from Geo Rust
      May 12, Liverpool, from Howell
      August 15, Leesburg, from John Scott
      December 15, Tazewell, From B. B.
      December 21, Warrenton, from J Scott
      From J Bradley
    - John Janney Letters, 1843. (Box-folder 6:19)
      January 10, Loudoun, from Colinian?
      January 25, Middleburg, from Chas Furr
      February 8, Middleburg, Alex Skinner
      February 12, from J Coalman
      May 26, Washington, from unreadable
      December 2, from unreadable
      From Howeay?
      Unknown letter
    - John Janney Letters, 1844. (Box-folder 6:20)
      January 10, Clarkstown, from Glouington?
      January 26, Charlestown, from Andreed ?
      February 21, from Eaton
      March 12, Baltimore, from unreadable
      May 28, Loudoun, legal document from P Knosy?
      July 8, Barnesville, from John Dueport
      July 17, Puffuldo, from unreadable
    - Official letter from Secretary of State Fletcher Webster, 1845. (Box-folder 6:21)
    - John Janney Letters, 1846. (Box-folder 6:22)
      February 5, goods ordered by JA Taylor
      March 11, Washington, unreadable
      April 23, Washington, from Alma
    - John Janney Letters, 1846. (Box-folder 6:23)
      March, official letter from Washington, D.C. signed by M Page
      September 14, Baltimore, from Hambliton Buckey
      September 19, Baltimore, from Woodward & Co.
      September 28, Baltimore, from Woodward & Co.
    - Legal letter from John Marmaduke, 1847. (Box-folder 6:24)
    - John Janney Letters, 1854. (Box-folder 6:25)
      February 1, Middleburg, from H Powell
      December 20, Middleburg, from H Powell
    - John Janney Letters, 1855. (Box-folder 7:1)
      April 8, Georgetown, from Walter Smith (governor)
      September 15, Philadelphia, from Gill
      October 9, Baltimore, bill of Fred Fickey
      From Upton
      Payments for AD Pollock
      Agreement between Sam Smith and Heird
      Signed by W Berry
    - Letter from the State of Maryland about a counterfit note, signed by SL Townsherd, 1861. (Box-folder 7:2)
    - John Janney Letters, 1861. (Box-folder 7:3)
      April 9, from John Porsle?
    - John Janney Letters, 1867. (Box-folder 7:4)
      February 12, Laurenceville, from James ?
      March 4, Baltimore, from H Keigheen
      December 22, Leeton Forest, from AD Pollock (father-in-law)
      December 30, Brook, unknown
    - Letter from McKenzie about hoping to reunite the country without slavery, 1864. (Box-folder 7:5)
    - Letter to Janney from William Collins of Baltimore, 1865. (Box-folder 7:6)
    - John Janney Letters, 1866. (Box-folder 7:7)
      April 4, from Seamma Manne?
      June 4, Middleburg, from Rogers
    - John Janney Letters, 1867. (Box-folder 7:8)
      April 16, Vicksburg, from Klein
      April 20, Norfolk, Ed Ribby
      May 22, Vicksburg, from Klein
      July 12, Vicksburg, from Klein
    - John Janney Letters, 1868. (Box-folder 7:9)
      January 20, Richmond, from R Duncee
      February 8, Norfolk, from Ed Ribby
      March, Baltimore,
    - John Janney Letters, 1869. (Box-folder 7:10)
      January 1, Richmond, W. Eshaart
      December 31, Alexandria, from GH Robinson
    - John Janney Letters, 1871. (Box-folder 7:11)
      January 2, Baltimore, Margaret Turner
      January 13, Baltimore, from Margaret Turner
      July 20, Alexandria, from GH Robinson
      October 5, Baltimore, Reese Bros.
      November 18, Alexandria, R Miller
    - Food accounts. (Box-folder 7:12)
      Ben Forgesan to P. Gautler
      Statement of work by Smith
    - Slave documents and letters, 1849-1852. (Box-folder 12:7)
      December 3, 1849, from Bredson?—wants Janney to buy his slave or find her a good home
      1850—Janney's tax receipt includes three negroes for $.96
      November 11, 1852, from HB Pollock—Wants to avoid selling his slaves south, one slave ran away but was caught.
    - John Janney Letters. (Box-folder 7:13)
      John Janney's real estate
    - Letter to John Janney—deals with a slave who paid for his freedom but was not given freedom because of new debts. (Box-folder 7:14)
    - Letters to Janney from Robert Miller, 1824-1830. (Box-folder 7:15)
      March 26, 1824, Alexandria
      March 17, 1826, Alexandria—Deals with the death of Jefferson and Adams
      March 24, 1827, Alexandria
      March 12, 1830 Alexandria
    - Letters to Janney from Blair and Rivs, 1852-1856. (Box-folder 7:16)
      December 15, 1852, Washington
      April 2, 1853, Washington
      December 26, 1854, Washington
      July 5, 1856, Washington
    - Letters to Janney from Muntz, President of Farmers (Meat?) Bank in Georgetown, 1848-1851. (Box-folder 7:17)
      January 29, 1848
      July 5, 1848
      November 9, 1848
      March 30, 1850
      July 1, 1851
    - Letters to Janney from McVeigh in Alexandria, 1847-1850. (Box-folder 7:18)
      July 5, 1847
      January 30, 1849
      November 9, 1849